Inventory of the Lieutenant Colonel Borkowski collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Lieutenant Colonel Borkowski collection
1939-1945
47016
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, government documents, bulletins, speeches and writings, and maps relating to Polish-Soviet relations, Polish military personnel and civilians deported to the Soviet Union, conditions in Poland during the German and Soviet occupations in World War II, and Polish military operations under French and British command.
Borkowski, Lieutenant Colonel, collector.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1947.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, government documents, bulletins, speeches and writings, and maps relating to Polish-Soviet relations, Polish military personnel and civilians deported to the Soviet Union, and conditions in Poland during the German and Soviet occupations in World War II. Includes circulars and instructions from the Polish Army Headquarters and Émigré Ministry of Defense in London to the military personnel of the Polish units fighting under Allied Command.
Anders, Wladyslaw, 1892-1970.; Sikorski, Władysław, 1881-1943.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Poland.; Poland--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; Poland--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--Poland.
- Documents of Polish Forces under French and British command, 1939-1944 (Box-folder 1: 1-3)
  - Instrukcja w sprawie rejestracji faktów, uwag i spostrzeżeń, dotyczących przygotowań i działań wojennych / L.dz.310-145/39 (Instruction on recording facts, comments, and observations relating to the war preparations and activities / file number), Paryż, 29.X.39, 1939 October 29 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Załącznik do Instrukcji powyższej / bez day i L.dz. (Attachment to the above instruction / no file number), undated
  - Nastroje wśród żołnierzy przepływających przez Stację Zborną / L.dz.14/Tj/40 (The mood among the soldiers passing through the Collecting Station / file number), Paryż, 14.I.40, two copies, 1940 January 14
  - Wytyczne Specjalne / L.dz.161/III.40 (Special Guidelines / file number), Paryż, dn.23.II.40, 1940 February 23
  - Wnioski z doświadczeń poczynionych w pierwszych walkach franc.-niem. / L.dz.288/III.40 (The conclusions from the experiences of the first French-German battles / file number), Paryż, dn.28.II.40, 1940 February 28
  - Dlaczego Alianci muszą zwyciężyć? (Why the Allies must win?), Paryż, marzec 1940, 1940 March
  - O listach drogą lotniczą / L.dz.428/Tjn./Og.Org/40 (The letters by air / file number), Paryż, dn.16.III.40, three copies, 1940 March 16
  - O korespondencji telegraficznej z częścią Polski okupowanej przez Sowiety / L.dz.269/Tjn/Og.Org/40 (The telegraphic correspondence with the Soviet-occupied part of Poland / file number), Paryż, 9.III.40, 1940 March 9
  - Sprowadzanie rodzin wojskowych do Francji / L.dz.288/Tj/40 (Bringing military families to France / file number), Paryż, dn.4.IV.40, 1940 April 4
    - a) Załącznik No. 1 (Attachment)
    - b) Załącznik No. 2 (Attachment)
  - Sprowadzanie rodzin wojskowych do Francji / L.dz.289/Tj/40 (Bringing military families to France / file number), Paryż, dn.20.IV.40, 1940 April 20
  - O urlopach żołnierzy do Nicei / L.dz.965/Pf/Og.-Org/40 (The soldiers' vacations in Nice / file number), Paryż, dn.8.V.40, two copies, 1940 May 8
  - Powściągliwość w korespondencji prywatnej / L.dz.12019/II.40 (Moderation in private correspondence / file number), Paryż, dn.10.V.40, 1940 May 10
  - Strzelanie z karabinów armji niemieckiej do samolotów nisko lecących/tłumaczenie instrukcji niemieckiej / L.dz.896/Tj.O.III/40 (Shooting with German Army guns to low-flying aircrafts/translation of the German instructions / file number), Paryż, dn.25.V.40, 1940 May 25
  - Biuletyn Sztabu N.Wodza No. l / L.dz.373/III.Tj.40 (Commander-in-chief Staff bulletin / file number), Londyn, dn.15.października 1940, 1940 October 15
  - Przemówienie N.Wodza na obiedzie dla Admiralicji / L.dz.1231, 1943
    - a) Rozdzielnik
    - b) Samo przemówienie
  - Program prac Sekcji Badań i Studiów Służby Intendentury, / L.dz.114/Tjn/43 (Work Program for Research Studies of Commissariat Service / file number), Londyn, dn.3.III.43, 1943 March 3
    - a) Zał. No. 1 (Attachment)
    - b) Zał. No. 2
    - c) Zał. No. 3
    - d) Zał. No. 4
    - e) Pismo przewodnie płk.Krajowskiego
    - f) Zadanie i zakres pracy Wydziału Studiów Adm.
  - O dywizji Berlinga / L.dz.1668/WPol/43, Londyn, 26.XI.43, 1943 November 26 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - a) Pismo przewodnie gen.Kukiela
    - b) Specjalny Komunika Informacyjny
  - Specjalny Komunikat Tajny No. 3/43 / L.dz.603/K.O./I/tj/43
  - Komunikat o Położeniu Politycznym / L.dz.2927/B.M./43, Londyn, 28.XII.43, two copies, 1943 December 28
  - Komunikat Tajny w Sprawie przekroczenia granicy Polski przez wojska sowieckie / L.dz.6/WPol/44, Londyn, 6.I.44, 1944 January 6
  - Komunikat w sprawie mowy Churchilla / L.dz.2217/B.M./44, Londyn, 25.II.44, 1944 February 25
  - Częściowy wykaz miejscowości, których nazwy zostały zmienione przez władze niemieckie / L.dz.1410/44, 14.III.44, 1944 March 14
  - Komunikat o roszczeniach sowieckich w stosunku do Polski / L.dz.2184/WPol/44, Londyn, 21.II.44, 1944 February 21
  - Komunikat o organizacji Sztabu N.Wodza / L.dz.268/GNW/44, Londyn, 10.III.44, 1944 March 10
  - Komunikat o Sytuacji na wschodnich ziemiach Polski / L.dz.2597/WPol/44, Londyn, 7.IV.44, two copies, 1944 April 7
  - O wysyłce paczek do Kraju / L.dz.1650/Bop/Og/44, Londyn, 15.V.44, 1944 May 15
    - a) Sam komunikat
    - b) Załączniki No. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 i 6, two copies
  - O powojennych problemach obrony/ze źródeł amerykańskich
    - a) Studium powojennych problemów obrony państwa
    - b) Studium problemów powojennej obrony narodowej
  - Biuletyn Informacyjny No. 80 / L.dz.3030/WPol/44, Londyn, 31.V.44, 1944 May 31
  - Wiadomości bieżące / L.dz.3177/WPol/44, Londyn, 23.VI.44, 1944 June 23
  - Sprawozdanie z działalności służby warsztatowej elektrotechnicznej II-go Korpusu w czasie akcji pod Monte Cassino / L.dz.365/Tj/SWEI/44, M.p.23.VI.44, 1944 June 23
  - Żołnierze Armji Sprzymierzonych w Italji /odezwa gen.Aleksandra, two copies
  - O Stosunkach polsko-sowieckich / L.dz.3314/WPol/44, Londyn, 14.VII.44, 1944 July 14
  - O zajęciu Wilna przewojska sowieckie / L.dz.3368/WPol/44, Londyn, 20.VII.44, 1944 July 20
  - Zasady polityki personalnej / L.dz.1387/Tjn.Pers44, Londyn, 1.VII.44, 1944 July 1
  - O aktach rachunkowych / L.dz.465/Tjn:Int.0.44, Londyn, 22.VII.44, 1944 July 22
  - O utworzeniu Szefostw Służb N.W./ L.dz.420/Kwat/44, Londyn, 22.VII.44, 1944 July 22
  - Oficerowie służby opieki /L.dz.2171/Bop/Og/Reg/44, Londyn, 24.VII.44, 1944 July 24
  - W sprawie zwrotów kosztów /L.dz.437/Int.M/tjn./44, Londyn, 31 lipca 1944 r., 1944 July 31
  - O antysemityzmie w Wojsku Polskim
    - Pismo przewodnie gen. Kukiela / L.dz.1092/WPol./43
    - Opracowanie M. Heitzmana / L.dz.855/WPol/43
  - Ćwiczenie "Obrona Stała"
    - a) Pismo płk.Smoleńskiego do Szefa oddz.Dwaterm. / L.dz.1187/Op/W., dn.26.VIII.44, 1944 August 26
    - b) Założenie wraz z 4-ma załącznikami
  - Poufny Biuletyn Informacyjny No. 88 / L.dz.3624/WPol/44, Londyn, dn.26.VIII.44, 1944 August 26
  - O stosunkach z Rosją Sow. / L.dz.3632/WPol/44, Londyn, dn.28.VIII.44, 1944 August 28
  - Ogólny plan organizacji i szkolenia jednostek i uzup. (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - a) Sam plan / L.dz.1739/Tjn/Wyszk.44, dn.4.IX.44, 1944 September 4
    - b) Zał. No. 1/tabela
    - c) Pismo gen.Głuchowskiego do N.Wodza
  - O szpitalach w W.Brytanii
    - a) Pismo gen.Głuchowskiego / L.dz.9550/44
    - b) Wykaz szpitali wojsk. w Szkocji / L.dz.9550/44
  - O transporcie powietrznym
    - a) Pismo przewodnie ppłk.Rehmana / L.dz.605/Kwat/Tjn/44, Londyn, dn.29.IX.44, 1944 September 29
    - b) Lotnictwo transportowe/Bryt. - Ameryk.
    - c) Zał. No. 1/transport morski a powietrzny
    - d) Tablice No. 1 i 2
  - O sprawach gospodarczych w szpitalach / L.dz.8050/Int.N.44, Londyn, dn.19.IX.44, 1944 September 19
  - Rozkaz awansowy na ppor. / L.dz.2619/Tjn.Pers.44, 17.X.44, 1944 October 17
  - Kompetenci Sztabu N.W. w sprawach pers. oficerów / L.dz.2800/Tjn.Pers.44, Londyn, 4.XI.44, 1944 November 4
  - Błędy słownictwa wojskowego
    - a) Pismo przewodnie Szefa Sztabu / L.dz.1141/Sztab/44, Londyn, 6.XI.44, 1944 October 6
    - b) Wykaz zasadniczych błędów
  - Stosunki z Rosją / L.dz.4050/WPol/44, Londyn, 13.XI.44, two copies, 1944 November 13
  - O polityce w wojsku / L.dz.1577/G.Z1/44, Londyn, 8.XI.44, two copies, 1944 November 8
  - Zasady wychowania w PSZ / L.dz.3523/B.Op/K.O./I/44, Londyn, 15.XII.44, 1944 December 15
  - Instrukcja o przymusowych nauczaniach analfabetów /L.dz.3525/B.Op/K.O./I/44, Londyn, 15.XII.44, 1944 December 15
    - a) Sama instrukcja
    - b) Załącznik No. 1
  - O stosunku do Czechów i Słowaków / L.dz.19/Pf/Sztab/45, Londyn, 8.II.45, 1945 February 8
  - Wytyczne Rządu dla Wojska / L.dz.206/WPol/45, Londyn, dn.14.II.45, 1945 February 24
  - O odsyłaniu odznaczeń brytyjskich / L.dz.243/B.M./Tjn/45, Londyn, dn.15.II.45, 1945 February 15
  - O opiece nad Polakami w Niemczech / L.dz.694/GNW/45, Londyn, dn.10.V.45, 1945 May 10
  - Dalsze instrukcje Rządu do Sił Zbrojnych / L.dz.204/WPol/45, Londyn, 13.II.45, 1945 February 13
  - O pogadankach w wojsku / L.dz.223/Sekr.InfS.Z./45, Londyn, dn.21.III.45, 1945 March 21
  - Rozkaz awansowy na stopnie ofic. w 1945 r. / L.dz.2830/Tjn.Pers.44, Londyn, dn.6.XI.44, 1944 November 6
- Polish-Russian relations, 1941 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Aperçu de la situation politique, économique et militaire de l'U.R.S.S.
  - Record of conversation between General Sikorski and Monsieur Maisky, July 5
  - Agreement draft, July 15
  - Polish-Soviet Agreement (draft sentence), July 15
  - Letter from General Sikorski to General Anders, August 2
  - Letter from General Sikorski to Stanisław Głąbinski, August 2
  - Letter from J. H. Retinger to General Sikorski, August 14
  - Letter from General Anders to General Sikorski, August 14
  - Letter from W. Arlet to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs in London
  - Letter from J. H. Retinger to General Sikorski, August 14
  - Notes from the conversation between Dr. J. Retinger and Commissioner of Foreign Affairs Wyszynski, August 15
  - Letter from Stanisław Grabski to General Sikorski, August 15
  - Letter from J. H. Retinger to General Sikorski, August 15
  - Letter from General Anders to General Sikorski, August 16
  - Letter from J. H. Retinger to General Sikorski, August 16
  - Proposals from J. H. Retinger to V. Molotov, August 22
  - Note from General Sikorski to J. H. Retinger
  - Letter from J. H. Retinger to General Sikorski (two copies), August 29
  - Private audience of Ambassador Kot with Kalinin, September 9
  - Notes from conversation between Ambassador Kot and Ambassador Steinhardt, Moscow, September 9
  - Conversation between Polish Ambassador Kot and Minister Wyszyński, September 10
  - Notes from the conversation between the Ambassador and Łozowski, September 17
  - Proposals from Polish Embassy to People's Commissariat for Foreign Affairs, regarding Polish radio, September 19
  - List of Polish journalists, writers, and artists accredited by Polish Embassy, September 20
  - Proposals from Polish Embassy regarding Polish press and propaganda, September 21
  - Letter from Ambassador Kot to the Minister of Foreign Affairs in London, September 22
  - Note about religion in Soviet Union, September 25
  - Conversation between Ambassador Bogomolow and J. Drohojowski, September 26
  - Letter from Szyszko-Bohusz to Retinger, September 28
  - Letter from camp in Soviet Union, September 30
  - Letter from camp in Soviet Union, October 1
  - Conversation between Ambassador Kot and Wyszyński, October 7
  - Letter from from Ambassador Kot to General Sikorski, October 8
  - Letter from Teresa Lipkowska to General Sikorski, October 11
  - Conversation between General Sikorski and Stalin, December 4
- Sosnkowski (Box-folder 1: 5)
- 1st Armored Division (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Polish-Soviet Agreement, 1941 (Box-folder 1: 7)
- Sytuacia zydow (Box-folder 1: 8)
- Inter-Allied Committee (Box-folder 1: 9)
- Inter-Allied Research Committee (Box-folder 1: 10)
- Various materials (Box-folder 1: 11)
- Wood industry (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Coal mines (lists and maps) (Box-folder 2: 2)
- Metallurgic industry (Box-folder 2: 3)
- Machinery industry (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Agricultural industry (Katowice region) (Box-folder 2: 5)
- Agricultural industry (Wrocław region) (Box-folder 2: 6)
- Chemical technology industry (Box-folder 2: 7)